No matter what you are building, if
you're working with AI coding
assistants, it is a lot more than just
prompts. It's all about creating
systems, workflows that can evolve to
fit your needs. I know it's tempting to
just wing it. But if you want to build
anything substantial, you do need
structure. There's a reason why we have
so many strategies around context
engineering like the PRP framework or
BMAD, the GitHub spec kit. There's a
million of them out there. And that's
actually the problem as well. It's easy
to get lost in the sauce, so to speak,
with all these different strategies and
how they apply to you. Now, the solution
to this problem is what I'm going to be
covering with you in this video. We're
going to be scrapping the notion of
existing frameworks like PRP and BMAD,
and we're going to be building our own.
I'll show you how it works. Because if
we can understand the philosophy and
strategies that go into all these
existing frameworks, not only can we use
them better because we actually
understand them, but also we can tweak
them to our needs and even build our own
workflows and systems. This is where the
power really comes into your hand. And
this diagram that you're looking at here
is everything I'm going to cover with
you in this video. It sums it up really
nicely because I want to keep things
simple and fundamental here. I want to
give you a process that you can apply
that'll take you super far with AI
coding assistance no matter what you are
making. So the primary mental model that
guides most of my coding is the
three-step process of planning, then
implementing and then validating. That's
we're going to build a workflow around.
And so I'll just go through at a really
high level everything that we're
covering here. Then we'll get into
detail and I'll show you a real example
as well. And so first of all, I always
start with planning. And I have a
multi-step process for this. I start
with vibe planning. That's what I like
to call it. We're basically just
exploring very free form the different
ideas that we want to implement for a
new project or the codebase for an
existing project. And then from there,
we create our initial requirements for
that new feature or new project. And
then we prepare all of the context so
the AI coding assistant has what it
needs to get the job done. And slash
commands are great for this. We're going
to be covering slash commands and sub
aents and other components of AI coding
in this video as well. And then once we
have all of the context we need, we want
to then execute on it to actually
produce our code. And creating a
predefined workflow through slash
commands is fantastic for this as well.
So we can define how we want to manage
tasks and research our codebase, those
kinds of things. And once we have the
code outputed, it is time for
validation. And we want to leverage AI
coding assistants to validate their own
work and then put ourselves in the
process as well. making sure that we can
really be the project manager for the AI
coding assistant. And then the last
thing that I'll be covering throughout
this video here is the different
concepts for AI coding assistance and
how they apply to different parts of our
workflow like global rules and sub aents
and slash commands. For example, we
don't actually want to use sub aents in
the implementation phase. So I'll talk
about how that works, really the
philosophy behind it. This will also
help you understand how these different
strategies work like PRP and BMAD. Now,
what I'll be building live here is not
the focus of this video. So, I thought I
would take this as an opportunity to do
something fun and different, showing you
something that I'm working on personally
because I've been overhauling my
productivity workflows recently,
switching to an app called Obsidian. It
is a free and local knowledge management
platform. You can kind of think of it
like Notion except there's also a ton of
open source plugins to extend it. I'm
working on some myself. I will probably
be creating a lot more content around
Obsidian in the future because you can
also use it as your second brain. It's
super cool and there's a lot of AI
integrations that I have been working on
including what I'm going to showcase in
this video. So, we have the co-pilot
chat on the right hand side. This is
connected to, you can see it right here
in the bottom right the Dynamis Obsidian
agent. I have my own AI agent that I
have running in Docker on my computer
and that is what Obsidian is connected
to. It's super cool. So, I can say tell
me about and then I can reference files
within Obsidian like the one that you're
looking at right here. I can send this
in and it's going to my custom agent.
This connection here is what we're going
to be building out in this video just as
an example for the custom workflows that
we're creating here. It's super cool.
Take a look at that. All right. Now,
let's dive into the process and we'll
start with the planning phase here,
which honestly is the most important
phase by far because if you're not
curating your context correctly for the
AI coding assistant, it will fall on its
face. And by the way, everything in this
video is going to be rather brief. I
just want to start with the basics here.
If you really want to dive deep into
mastering AI coding assistance with me,
definitely come be a part of the
half-day workshop that I'm hosting on
September 27th. This is where we really
dive deep. All of my strategies in one
place for getting the most out of AI
coding assistance. So, hope to see you
there. Link below. Definitely check it
out. I am going to be pouring so much
value into that workshop. And so, right
now, you kind of get a taste actually of
a lot of what we're going to be covering
here. I want to help you build your own
AI coding workflows so you can
understand the philosophy and strategies
that go into all these different
frameworks. And so, with that, we can
start with the planning phase. Now, the
first thing I always do to start the
planning phase is vibe planning. Now,
hear me out on this. If you've seen my
AI coding content in the past, you know
that I'm not a fan of vibe coding, but
that's different because that's when we
get into the actual implementation. We
definitely want a lot of structure and
validation there. But when we're in the
planning phase initially, all we're
doing is exploring ideas, architecture,
concepts, figuring out our tech stack.
We're doing that with our AI coding
assistant as our research companion. And
I purposefully do not want this to be
structured because I want a more
freeformed mindset as I'm working in
this initial phase. And so for new
projects, this means researching online
resources, previous projects that you've
implemented. I actually love to do this
where I'll create an examples folder in
my codebase and take existing projects
and put it there and research that with
my coding assistant. And then for
existing projects, it's generally
researching and analyzing the existing
codebase to see where our new feature is
going to fit in. And of course, this
isn't an exhaustive list. It's really
whatever you want to do to have a
conversation with your AI coding
assistant so you're both on the same
page of what needs to be fully planned
and implemented. And so once you have
that conversation with the coding
assistant, within that same context
window, I'll have it help me create what
I like to call an initial MD. This is
the first file that we create for our
planning. Just a simple markdown
document. The goal is to produce a
markdown doc with a detailed feature
request, otherwise known as a PRD. This
is the kind of document that's more high
level, the kind of thing you could give
to another human to describe what you're
looking to build. So, at this point,
we're not super specific to prompting
strategies for the coding assistant yet.
And so, for a new project, generally,
you want this to be very high level. a
simple MVP for the application you want
to build, including a lot of references
to the supporting documentation and
examples that you found in the vibe
planning stage. And then for the
existing project, it's pretty similar,
but it's going to be a lot more focused
and detailed that specific feature you
want to build into the existing
codebase, including a lot of references
to what I like to call integration
points. The files that have to be
edited, maybe the files you want to
reference for architecture. Again, all
of those things that you discover with
the coding assistant in the vibe
planning stage. So once we have this
initial MD, that's when we want to take
our requirements and turn it into a
full-fledged prompt for the AI coding
assistant. And this is really where the
strategies around context engineering
come into play. You've probably seen
this diagram on my channel before, but I
recreated it from scratch in Excaladraw.
Hope you're proud of me. I put way too
much effort into making this. It's kind
of silly, but anyway, we have RAG,
providing external documentation to our
coding assistant, memory, like our
conversation history. We have task
management. This is super important for
the planning phase, and we'll talk about
this in a little bit. And then, of
course, we have prompt engineering,
which is a lot about how do we take our
initial request and craft it in a way
where we have a plan of attack for the
coding assistant. And so, the goal in
this stage, we are producing a second
markdown document. So, we take our
initial MD and we produce a detailed set
of goals, tasks, and resources for the
AI coding assistant. Basically giving it
everything it needs to get the job done
effectively. So, we're taking our PRD,
turning it into a full-fledged
implementation prompt. And by the way,
this is exactly what the PRP framework
accomplishes that I cover on my channel.
And so I'm starting from the basics
here, but it's kind of cool how like it
naturally progresses into kind of a
light bulb moment where it's like, "Oh
yeah, PRP, that totally makes sense
because that's exactly what we're
doing." When you generate a PRP, you're
taking your initial requirements and
turning it into a much more structured
document for the coding assistant that
has things like the task list that you
want to knock out, your desired codebase
structure, your success criteria, all
the documentation examples that you
wanted to reference. That is what we're
creating with our planning document. And
there are a lot of tools to help us get
the job done here. I'll show you Archon
in a little bit with our live example,
the PRP framework, of course, even
simple web search tools that we have
with things like cloud code. That is a
part of the rag that we have for context
engineering and archon is also for rag
by the way and also our task management.
And then a lot of other tools coming out
like the GitHub spec kit is rather new,
really cool, provides a lot of commands
to help us do a very similar thing that
we're doing here with the vibe planning
and then you know creating our initial
requirements and creating the plan.
GitHub spec kit does a lot of that. And
so again, understanding the philosophies
here that go behind these different
strategies. All right, let's get into
the codebase now because I want to show
you how this works in action. Now, for
brevity sake, I already had the
conversation complete, but I'll walk you
through my general process, how I'm
applying the principles to start to
create this AI coding workflow that I'll
showcase here. That is just an example
of the kind of thing that you can build.
And so, first of all, we're starting
with a brand new conversation with cloud
code. And this works no matter your
coding assistant, of course. And the
first thing I do whenever I start a new
conversation working in an existing
codebase like I'm doing for this
Obsidian integration is I will run a
primer slash command. And so we're
starting to get into slash commands
here. Slash commands are simply prompts
that you want to turn into reusable
workflows which very much goes with the
theme that we have here. creating a
system for AI coding both with mental
models and also with literal workflows
that we have created as these markdown
slashcomands here. And so what the
primer does is it lists out instructions
for files to read to quickly catch the
AI coding assistant up to speed on our
project when we're starting a new
conversation. And so that way it kind of
feels like our coding assistant has been
working with us on this project for a
while now, but it is actually a fresh
conversation. And so it does a bunch of
research through the key files in my
codebase. And then at this point I'm
ready to move to the vibe planning and
slash commands are pretty important for
most stages of our workflow here. Really
every single stage. And so I have this
part of the diagram here talking about
this for the planning stage. This is
where we want to set up our global
rules, the key instructions for our
coding assistant. And then we use sub
aents and slash commands to automate
parts to create those workflows for
parts of our planning stage. And we do a
lot of that for validation and
implementation as well. Except we don't
use sub agents for implementation. I'll
talk about that in a second here. So
yeah, we're in the VI planning stage
now. And this is where, like I said, we
don't have structured prompts. It's
super basic here. I just describe at a
high level what I want to build because
I want my AI agent to be able to connect
to my Obsidian vault. I give an example
that I pulled from a past project that I
want it to reference. This is just the
high level. Let's start to get into the
code. Then once we do this exploration
and we're confident in its understanding
and you can kind of elaborate more and
and fix up some of its understanding,
you make sure you're on the same page
with it. Then you will go and create the
initial MD. And so you on the same page,
you did your planning. Now we start to
add in our structure. And so in this
case, I'm calling my initial MD OpenAI
API compatibility. It's just a markdown
document with that initial request that
we have for our AI coding assistant. So
we have the feature that we want at a
high level, the endpoints that we want
to build, some examples of how we want
to interact with our agent. It's not
super super planned out at this point,
but this is our initial request that
we're then going to turn into the full
plan. That's the key here is at this
point we're just creating our initial
MD. And so we have that built out. And
now at this point that is the end of our
first conversation. We want to move now
to another fresh conversation because we
want to move on to the next stage of our
workflow. Taking that request and
turning it into the full plan with all
of the context engineering. And so I've
created yet another slash command for
this part of the workflow. So I'm
calling it create plan.md. And again,
this is just an example of what your
planning workflow can look like. You can
build this however you want. Just
generally, you'd want to kind of follow
the principles that I have covered in
this diagram. And so, I walk you through
this three-step process. And now, I'm
just building slashcomands and sub aents
around this general flow, doing some
things that are kind of more specific to
my project as well. And so, you can
build these kind of flows to however
works best for what you are creating.
And so for my create plan, basically I'm
just telling it to take the requirements
document, that's what we just finished
creating, and then go through a few
different phases. So read and understand
the requirements. We have a research
phase where I wanted to use web
searching for rag and also archon if it
is available. And then I also have this
codebase analyst sub agent. So I created
a sub agent that it calls upon to do a
lot of that extensive research. And not
to get too deep into sub agents right
now, but they're very powerful because
they have their own context window. So
they can do a ton of research and then
output a summary of that without it
polluting our primary conversation. So
we keep our context window concise and
focused. And so this sub agent just does
a lot of research around our existing
codebase to figure out exactly what our
plan should look like. So we need to
create you know that implementation plan
task by task our desired codebase
structure the documentation we want to
reference and the codebase analyst and
this whole slash command helps us create
that and so I'll go back into the
conversation and kind of show you what
that looks like. So first of all I ran
the create plan here with the
requirements document passed in as my
argument in the command and it starts by
calling the codebase analyst sub aent.
So it does a ton of research. It figures
out exactly how we're going to be
integrating this new feature in our
codebase. It does some rag searches with
archon. It does some codebase example
searches and then it produces our plan.
And so this is kind of taking that
initial MD to the next level with all of
that context engineering. And so these
things I've been speaking to, we'll find
those here. Like here is our step by
step all the tasks that we want to
implement. And it gets really granular
here which is always good. If you want
to be specific with AI coding
assistance, that's exactly what this
plan gives us. We have the different
files that we need to modify, the ones
that we need to create, existing
patterns to follow, everything that it
needs to get the job done. Super cool.
And we have the success criteria as
well. Maybe I could add like a desired
codebase structure, but it's more about
editing existing files. So I think like
for what I'm building here, this plan is
absolutely perfect. So now that we have
the plan created, that is the end of
what I've gotten to so far. So now with
that comprehensive plan, well, first of
all, I'd recommend validating it,
actually making some adjustments with
the help of the coding assistant if
necessary. But once you're confident in
the plan, then it is time to move on to
implementation. Now, for implementation,
the most important thing is to have a
workflow that guides the coding
assistant on how to knock out the tasks
one by one. And the task management here
is the most important thing, especially
if you're trying to do quite a bit in
one request. If the coding assistant
tries to do too much at once, that's
when you have a lot of hallucinations.
And so tasks are your way to have a
larger request, but still have it be
very focused and granular on one little
thing each time. Like if we go back to
our planning document, you could see
that like we have very granular tasks
that we're having a knockout one by one.
And so we're going to create another
slash command to define this workflow.
And exactly what your slash command
looks like depends entirely on what
you're doing for your task management.
And so in my case, I'm using archon for
task management. And so my workflow
speaks a lot to how exactly I want to
use archon. Now it's not the case that
you have to use archon. That's the point
here is this is just an example of my
workflow. So it's creating all these
tasks here for this OpenAI API
compatible implementation. But you could
be using Cloud Taskmaster or another
Markdown document to manage your tasks.
However you want to do it, even just the
internal task management tools that we
have within these coding assistants like
Cloud Code. The important thing is just
to create a workflow around the task
management. And so when I go to my
execute plan here, I'll just show you
really quickly at a high level what this
looks like. And this might end up
looking a lot different for your
workflow, but I want to read my plan
that I've created. This could be a PRP
if we're using the PRP framework or, you
know, it could be the project brief if
we're using the BMAD method. And then I
want to set up the project in Archon if
it isn't already. Create all these
tasks. I want to analyze the code. And
then I have this cycle here where I need
to mark a task as to-do or doing. And
then it'll go through that task and then
move it to review and then move on to
the next task. And it'll do that in a
cycle until everything is done. And then
it'll move on to validation. And we
actually have a sub agent to help with
validation as well. So it'll execute
this guy to within its own context
window, create a bunch of tests, and
make sure that our code is good, and
then report back to our primary coding
assistant if there's anything that needs
to be fixed up. And so yeah, generally
my process around validation is while
the coding assistant is running, I will
validate to make sure that it's using my
MCP servers properly, that it's editing
the right files and looking in the right
places, I generally watch it at least
kind of closely to test these things.
And then once we have the code outputed,
this is where our plan should also speak
to how the AI coding assistant can
validate its own work. And then we want
to be a part of this process as well.
Performing a code review because we
don't want to vibe code. We want to
actually look at and understand the code
that is being produced and then running
any kind of manual tests that we want to
like actually talking to the agent in
Obsidian like we'll see at the end of
this video here. And sub aents can be
great for validation because again we
want isolated context windows to not
pollute our primary conversation so that
we can have a sub agent run a bunch of
different tests to make sure that
everything is rock solid. And one last
thing for validation. There's another
agent that I love using to review my
work. You can think of it as another
validation sub aent and that is Code
Rabbit. an AI powered code review
platform and they are sponsoring this
video but I do use them every single day
for my work and it's free for open
source projects so naturally I've
integrated code rabbit with archon every
single pull request that is made to the
archon GitHub repository is
automatically reviewed by the code
rabbit agent it analyzes my codebase
deeply and my poll request it
understands how it affects things and
outlines that here it gives me a
beautiful sequence diagram for every PR
it suggests reviewers and of course we
have the allimportant actual code review
here with the changes that it recommends
and I will literally take these and give
them to claude code or whatever AI
coding assistant I'm using. So, it's
become a crucial part of my development
workflow, and I'm just very thankful to
have Code Rabbit for Archon, especially
with all the poll requests that we're
managing every single week. And they
have a CLI tool now, so you can use Code
Rabbit not just to review your PRs in
GitHub, but now you can also use it as
one of your agents reviewing things
locally when you're developing on your
machine. Code Rabbit also offers free
trials for their paid tiers and is free
for open- source software like Archon
like I mentioned earlier. And the
reviews with the CLI and IDE tools are
free with rate limits that apply of
course. And so if you've been feeling
overwhelmed with the amount of code that
you've been creating with AI tools, this
is your ticket to maintain quality
without slowing down. I'll have a link
to Code Rabbit in the description. I
would definitely recommend trying them
out. So on to implementation in action.
And this is pretty simple overall
because we did so much of the work up
front in the planning stage. So now
thanks to the plan that we've generated
that has all the components of context
engineering. All we have to do is
execute our predefined workflow passing
in the plan that we have created. So
again we have the execute plan/comand
where we take in our requirements. We
break it down into all those tasks. And
in this case I'm doing everything in
archon. And so I went through this
implementation already. So, we have all
the tasks in done. It knocked it out
100%. Is actually really incredible. And
so, I'll go back to the terminal here
and show you uh the conversation that we
have. And so, it's partially cut off
because there's a lot of work that it
did here. But, yeah, we just sent it in
to implement literally everything. And
it goes for a while here. There's a lot
that it's taking care of, but I have
quite a bit of trust in the coding
assistant because of all the context
that I gave it and how things are split
up between the different tasks. And you
can see that was doing a lot of the task
management with archon here as it is
changing things. So it's interled
managing tasks making changes and then
going through that cycle. And then at
the very end here we have validation.
And validation is kind of mixed into
implementation as well. And that is
where we invoke our specialized
validator sub aent. And so it went for
quite a while here. Actually probably
longer than I really needed it to go. It
did a lot of validating with unit
testing and other things to make sure
that our code is rock solid. And the
important thing that I want to call out
here is that for the validation that's
when we go back to using sub aents. So
planning and validation we use sub aents
but I on purpose did not use any sub
aents during the implementation. And the
reason for that is when we're actually
making the code changes doing the
implementation, we want everything to
remain in the primary context window for
cloud code or whatever our AI coding
assistant is. If we have different sub
aents implement different parts of our
codebase, they're not really
communicating with each other and memory
is not shared between them. So you start
to have conflicting changes and
overlapping changes. It becomes a mess
when you use sub aents for the actual
code creation. And so generally I always
use sub agents for the research upfront
and then also having a validator
specialist so I can give a very specific
system prompt to this agent for how to
validate my code. So that's the really
important distinction I want to make
there. Otherwise for slash commands I'm
using them in every single part of the
implementation like you saw. And then
global rules. I haven't covered too much
in this video, but really this is what
you'd set up in your planning phase
initially. When you're trying to just
think at a high level like what are the
instructions that I want my coding
assistant to follow literally no matter
what I'm doing, starting the project
from scratch, adding in a new feature,
doing a bug fix, there are a lot of
those kind of golden rules that you want
to put within your claw.md whatever that
file is called for your coding
assistant. And then of course the last
step here is our own review. You
definitely want to perform a code review
on everything that was outputed by your
coding assistant. Otherwise, you're
still just reverting back to Vive
coding. So, perform a review and then
run manual tests as well. Like I have my
agent API running again in Docker. I
have the connection already set up in
Obsidian. So, I'll just show you this
really quick. I'll go into my chat
window here and I'll say summarize. And
then I'll just reference this whole
diagram that we've been going through
throughout this video. So, I'll send
this to send to my agent. It's
communicating to literally what we just
built using the OpenAI API compatible
endpoints. And there we go. We have a
summary of the full workflow based on
our diagram here. Absolutely beautiful.
The implementation is flawless. And now
we have this workflow that we can use
for other things as well. I mean the
whole planning slash commands and primer
that I had and the sub agents for
validating and executing and my whole
process for task management in archon
like it's not actually that specific to
this specific implementation. Like I can
take this and reuse it for anything that
I want to build. And that is the main
thing that I'm trying to describe to you
in this video is how you can create
these combinations of rules and sub
agents and slash commands and even just
like a mental model of how you plan then
implement and validate and like that
becomes your process that you can reuse
for anything. you've now built a system
for working with AI coding assistants.
And even when you start to incorporate
other things like the PRP framework or
the GitHub spec kit, you're still
following that same mental model, just
using those approaches to basically
augment what you have and you can tweak
it to your needs. So that's everything
that I've got for you today. If you
appreciated this video and you're
looking forward to more things around AI
coding and building out these kinds of
workflows, I would really appreciate a
like and a subscribe. And with that, I
will see you in the next